look, "labes".
guarda. labes.
fall, collapse, ruin, destruction, plague,
caduta, crollo, rovina, distruzione, flagello, peste.
pest, fault, shame, disgrace, dishonour.
difetto, vergogna, infamia e disonore.
but why?
ma perché?
why would a man play these little tricks?
perché un uomo deve fare questi giochetti?
because he's cruel?
perché è crudele?
or because he's unhappy?
o perché è infelice?
mum always said he was a passive man.
mamma ha sempre detto che era un passivo.
but he isn't passive!
ma quale passivo!
being passive is his strength, not his weakness.
la passività è stata la sua forza, non la sua debolezza.
you don't have a career lasting 40 years if you're not smart.
uno non fa una carriera lunga quarant'anni, se non è furbo.
he was just an ordinary man...
lui era un uomo banale che ha fatto
who made a career from saying clever things.
carriera dicendo cose acute.
he was ordinary-clever.
era un banale acuto.
while mum is exactly what happened to her.
invece mamma è quello che le è successo.
- mum fought for what she wanted! - she fought for what she didn't want.
- ha lottato per ciò che voleva. - ha lottato per ciò che non voleva.
and nearly died.
ed è quasi morta.
- where would they put all their stuff? - we'll throw it all away.
- dove metterebbero la roba? - buttiamo via tutto.
dad keeps all the crap he wrote when he was thirteen years old.
nostro padre tiene le cazzatelle che scriveva a tredici anni.
he's hardly Dante Alighieri, dammit!
ma non è Dante Alighieri, cazzo.
he's a man who wrote nonsense for the radio, then tv, that's all.
ha scritto sciocchezze per la tv e la radio, niente di più.
there are things in this house you don't know about it.
in questa casa ci sono cose che tu non sai.
- tell me. - i won't tell you, i'll show you.
- spiegati. - no, ti faccio vedere.